Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna be looking
at math skills to ACE chemistry.
In particular, we're gonna be looking
at the world of percentages, especially
in how you can use them in different
unit conversion and word problems.
We use percentages in chemistry very
often to show concentration of different
substances, whether it's in masses.
Whereas volumes, and we also
very commonly will see it in the
lab, in the form of different
percentages, percent yields as well.
So we're gonna be going through a lot of
different examples to help us understand
this concept further, so that way you
can do well in your chemistry class.
The first thing though is before we
do anything, is understanding really
what the true meaning of a percent is.
Which, if you look at that word
when you hear per cent, well that
per right, it comes back again as
it did in dimensional analysis.
That is a conversion term.
So whenever we see a percent, it tells
you that this is going to be out of 100.
So this is in itself a big fraction
term where we are going to have
it some kind of number out of 100.
So whenever we see this, we're gonna go
through many different examples of how
we can show how a percent is out of 100.
So think a cent, like if you think a sense
as in money or sense in century, right?
A hundred.
That will help you remember that.
So let's dive in into many examples
of how we can utilize percents.
Percentages are gonna come at
you in two, in a couple different
ways to main ones to be specific.
One is gonna be decimals to percentages.
Whenever we see a decimal to a
percentage, that means that we have
to multiply it by 100 in order to
get it into its percentage form.
So for example, whenever we see a decimal,
let's say if I have 0.373 as a decimal,
well, alls we have to do is remember
to multiply that by a hundred, and that
will show us that we have a percent.
Right.
Sometimes we're given it in the
form of a percentage, meaning that
we can divide that number by 100
to show the same general idea.
So let's say if I have 94.2%, is
the term given to me in a problem?
Well, if I divide that number by
100 to make it a decimal or make
it a usable number for ourselves.
We could quickly see that.
Okay, that's gonna be equal
to 0.942 in decimal notation.
So this can come in two different ways.
We will also see a very common term
known as percent composition, meaning
that when we go through this, well
it's telling you it can be by mass,
maybe by volume, mass over volume.
But the whole idea with any
percent is that it is the amount of
something or the part of something.
Over the whole, in this case,
we're gonna be referring to mass.
So if I have the part of the
mass divided over the entire
thing, well that's a percent.
One way to look at that is if you
think of a, maybe a slice of pizza
or some pizza, for example, if I have
an entire pizza and I just want one
slice, well a slice, there's usually
eight slices in a pizza, right?
So if you do one divided by eight,
that's telling you a percentage, right?
It's not necessarily in mass, but it's
still a percent part over the whole.
So in this case, when we do mass percent,
we, this is a very common thing for us to
figure out how much of a specific compound
or molecule is within our substance.
So how can we exactly interpret that?
Well, if I have the following example
here where if I say I have stainless
steel, which is an alloy, meaning it's
made of multiple metals and it's made
up of the falling elements, chromium,
nickel, moly, dium, molybdenum, and iron.
Stainless seal is 22.4% nickel.
So how can we try to define
this as a fraction for
ourselves or a decimal, right?
So this case we're given a percentage.
So if we go from percentage to decimal,
meaning that it's part over the hole.
Now, if you also remember per cent, right,
we have a bunch of little things that we,
we have all swirling around our brain.
Well being that this is a percent.
The way that we can end up
determining how, what is our part?
Our part in this case is going to be, we
have 22.4%, which is the same thing as
saying, oh, I have 22.4 grams of nickel,
but remember per cent, so out of 100,
so we have 22.4 grams a nickel, all out
of a hundred grams of stainless steel.
So we can show this as a fraction,
not only just as a decimal.
We could convert this to a decimal.
If you do 22.4 divided by 100 in your
calculator, you will quickly see like how
we did earlier, that this will be 0.24.
Would also be your number
for this case, right?
If you wanted to know exactly
what it was in terms of a decimal.
So it's the ratio that we have here, but
this is something we can use for ourselves
as a very helpful conversion term.
Let's do a bunch of examples with this.
So when it comes to trying to define these
in different problems, sometimes you might
be given a problem like this one, which
says, if magnesium chloride, so MgCl2.
Contains 25.5% magnesium by mass, and
the mass of the compound is 213 grams.
What is the mass of magnesium?
So with this one there, there's many
different terms we are given here.
So what we have to do is
define our givens, just like a
dimensional analysis problem.
One thing that we are given
is we have a percent right?
We have 25.5% magnesium.
One of the first things we can do for
ourselves is define that percent, because
it is a conversion term in disguise.
So when we have this, it is 25.5 grams
of magnesium, and it told us that the
problem told us the compound is MgCl2.
So that is our whole, right?
A hundred grams of MgCl2.
Great.
We have our fraction.
That's the hardest part,
defining what that percent means.
Now, what else were we
given in the problem?
We were also told that our compound is
213 grams, so we'll put that down as well.
So MgCl2 is 213 grams.
Our desired piece of information
is that we want to know what
is the mass of magnesium.
So what we have to do is set this
up like a unit conversion problem.
So how can we do that?
Well, we have two options to start with.
Either the massive magnesium
chloride or a unit conversion.
And if you remember from previous
videos of providing unit conversions
and dimensional analysis, we
never start with a conversion term
unless we necessarily have to.
We have a term that is by itself.
So we are gonna start
with this guy here, right?
It is by itself.
So let us write down
our tea tables, right?
So when we write down a tea table,
right, we can write that down.
We have our 213 grams of MgCl2,
and it's a very important to make
sure you do write the identity of
the compound you're working with.
'cause notice the percent
it has both pieces, right?
So magnesium and magnesium chloride, right
elements and compounds we need to specify.
The next part is 25.5 grams
of magnesium will be on top.
A hundred grams of MgCl2 is on bottom.
Now why did I write the, the conversion
there and not try to flip it?
Well, the big idea is remember, units
have to be opposites of one another
right in order from the cancel.
So being the MgCl2, that is
the unit we're looking for.
It is opposite of our other unit here.
So we can see that, alright,
these are gonna cancel.
And even the better part is that
this is going to leave us only with
a mag massive magnesium, which is
what we wanted from the problem.
So when you click this in your calculator
rate two 13 times 25.5 divided by
100, and that will give you your final
number of 54.3 grams of magnesium.
Right?
So that would be your final part.
This is our answer here.
So one to the next part, percent yield.
Percent yield is a common concept found
within the laboratory environment.
When you're doing an experiment and you
are making a compound after a long day
experiment, you're going to weigh it.
When you do that, you will
get an actual mass, which is
referred to as your actual yield.
Now, did you do a good
job when you made it?
Who knows, right?
But there's a way you can tell.
If you do stoichiometry, you can actually
calculate the theoretical yield or the
number that you're supposed to get if
everything goes to plan and is perfect.
So if you take those two numbers,
actual times that are divided by
the theoretical and times that
by 100%, you will get 8% yield.
So let's try this with a certain problem.
We'll make it, we'll make it simpler.
Take out the stoichiometry if you
have 34.2 grams of copper fluoride.
Are actually formed in lab and
you calculate the 30 theoretical
yield to be 47.5 grams.
What is the percent yield when
you are going through this?
So we lay it out just like
the problem we had above.
We have our actual and theoretical,
so we have to map out every number
one thing that we'll see, the
actual yield is equal to 34.2 grams.
Then we also have that are theoretical.
Yield is equal to 47.5 grams, right?
We have all these values in our, in our
problem, so let us set it up when we
are trying to get our percent yield.
We're going to plug these
numbers in to our equation here,
so actual over theoretical.
So we'll take our 34.2 grams.
Divide that by 47.5 grams and then we
will times that by a hundred percent.
When we are to do that, we are
gonna get a value of 72.0%.
It's R percent yield, which is pretty good
for a first time experiment, especially
when you're in general chemistry.
The closer you're to a hundred percent,
the better you did, but there's
always gonna be some errors along
the way, which is perfectly okay.
You just have to think
about it and analyze it.
Alright, onto the next type of problem.
If the percent yield is 82.4%
and the theoretical yield is 9.34
grams, what is the actual yield?
So doing another percent yield
problem, but the opposite.
So in this case, we have
82.4% is our yield, and we're
given the theoretical yield.
And if you remember, that's on
the bottom of our denominator.
So let's set that up.
9.34 grams.
And this is all times a hundred percent.
We want to know what the actual yield is.
So let's do the math.
First thing, just like our original
steps from earlier, the first
beginning of this video, divide by 100.
Notice how that's the
first thing we will do.
So when we divide by a hundred on both
sides, you will get 0.824 is equal
to the actual yield divided by 9.34.
Our next step, we are going to
multiply 9.34 grams by each side
that's gonna cancel terms, right?
So let's.
Show how the other ones
are gonna cancel too.
We'll divide that 9.34, or
sorry, multiply it by each side.
And what we will get is our actual yield,
and that is going to be a number of 7.696.
Okay?
So actual yield is 7.696 grams.
Now keep that in mind.
Write your units now.
Is that the right answer?
Well, big figs, right?
So everything in the problem was three
sig figs, so we have to make sure we
round this to three significant figures.
When we do that, our final answer is gonna
be 7.70 grams is our actual yield, and
that's how you can do a longer version
of this problem when you're not given
every little piece, you know the yield.
We need to calculate a missing piece.
Okay, one to the next
one to our last problem.
We have solutions and density.
In this case, what we are trying to do is
find the volume of a solution, which is a
mixture of different compounds together.
In this case, we have a Boba tea
solution, so we got boba and tea and
sugar and water all mixed together.
When you have a solution,
it's all percents, right?
We have the part over the whole.
In this one, what we're trying to do is
find the volume in milliliters of a Boba
tea solution that is 15% of sugar, right?
There's that conversion term.
And that says by mass too, and
it contains 79.2 grams of sugar
with a density of 1.04 grams.
We have all these important terms.
Our first piece, which is percent,
so we have 15% of sugar here.
So if I have 15% sugar, that's
the same thing as saying that
I have 15 grams of sugar.
All over a hundred grams of solution.
Our next part, which was our sugar
itself, is 79.2 grams of sugar,
and that is a term by itself.
Our last term is the density, where what
we have is 1.04 grams of our solution
all over one milliliter of our solution.
So the density of it.
Now, how do we go through
and do this problem?
Well, just like any dimensional analysis
problem, we will write out our tea table
and start with the term that is by itself.
So the term that's by
itself is the sugar, right?
We'll start with that.
And with that it'll help us lead our
unit cancellation grams per sugar.
We can use our percent to
help us do that, right?
You can see grams per
sugar in that percent.
So if I put the percent portion
on the bottom here, Where I have
my 15 grams of sugar, a hundred
grams of our solution on top.
Notice how the grams of sugar
will now officially cancel out.
As a result, our next portion is alright.
Well use the density,
convert it to milliliters.
We have that 1.04 grams of the
solution is equivalent to one
milliliter of that solution.
So that will cancel as
all grams cancels grams.
When we go through that process,
we are gonna do our last step,
so 79.4 multiplied by 100.
Then we will divide
everything on the bottom.
When we do that, we're gonna get a
final number of 507.69 milliliters.
Now, as always, is that the
correct amount of sig figs
when you're going through this?
Um, when you are trying to go through
these, right, we can see that we
need two sig figs due to the percent.
How would we round this?
Well, we gotta round that
to the second sig fig spot.
So what this is going to
round to is approximately 510.
Milliliters as our final solution.
So I hope that this video helped.
It went through many different examples
of how you can see percents in chemistry.
There are other ways that you will
see them, but this covered all the
basic areas that you could see them.
Just remember two things.
Percent is out of 100, and if
you remember part over the whole.
Times 100% you will be able to solve
any of these types of problems.
I wish you the best luck as you go
through these and I'll keep rolling
out videos and please hit that like and
subscribe button if you like this and
if it helped you, and hopefully this
will help you pass chemistry and further
even ace it, which will even be better.
I'll see you next time.
Until later, this is Dr.
Dan.
I'll see you all later now.
Bye.